[Music]
Dental cavities may be Humanity's most
prevalent disease affecting 35% of the
global population the average number of
decayed missing and filled teeth has
been estimated at more than two by age
12 in the United States the oral health
of our elderly may also be in a state of
decay with 1/4 of elderly persons
missing all their teeth and an estimated
100 billion dollar of all that is due to
Sugar Sugar consumption is considered
the one and only cause of cavities
though often referred to as a
multifactorial condition the other
factors the bacteria the plaque the
saliva the brushing the flossing appear
to just have mitigating influences all
the other factors simply modify the
speed by which sugar causes cavities
without sugars the chain of causation is
broken and the disease does not occur
we might not even need all that stuff if
we could just get rid of added sugar
studies dating back decades ago showed
that in countries where sugar
consumption was very low Dental cavities
was almost non-existent and new analyses
show that the lifelong burden of
cavities increases as sugar intake
increases from zero the most
comprehensive National Data are from
Japan before during and after World War
II where the incidence of cavities
tracked per capita sugar intake as a
dropped from about 8% of calories down
to just
0.1% less than a teaspoon a week before
rebounding to about
14% such studies show that cavities
continued to occur even when sugar
intake comprised only 2 to 3% of chloric
intake given that more extensive disease
in adults doesn't appear to manifest if
sugar intakes are limited to less than
3% of caloric intake a public health
goal to limit sugar intake to below 3%
has been
recommended this led to the suggestion
that traffic light labels you know Mark
anything above 2.5% added sugars as high
that would make even comparatively low
sugar breakfast cereals such as Cheerios
red light Foods the recommended 3% cap
on total daily intake of added sugars
wouldn't even allow for a single average
serving for young children of any of the
top 10 breakfast cereals most heavily
advertised to them obviously soda is off
the table one can has nearly two days
worth the American Academy of pediatric
dentistry adopted the more pragmatic
goal recommending sugar intake stay
below 5% for children and Adolescence
matching to the world health
organizations conditional
recommendations for both children and
adults that's about where sugar dropped
to in Iraq when they were under
sanctions and it cut cavity rates in
half within just a few years of course
the sanctions may have cut other things
like children's lives short though that
was apparently fake news a consequence
of government manipulation anyway if we
were really interested in minimizing
disease the ideal goal would be to drop
the intake of free sugars to zero
meaning added sugars they're not talking
about sugars naturally found in breast
milk or the intrinsic sugars found in
fruit but when it comes to added sugars
there does not seem to be a Thresh old
for sugar intake below which there are
no adverse effects an exponential
increase in cavity rates for sugar
intakes even starting as low as
1% yeah maybe we could get rid of
cavities if there was no sugar in the
diet wrote a Kellogg's funded researcher
this ideal is Impractical the
dictatorial use of foods friendly to the
teeth might promote dietary celibacy not
acceptable to all individuals instead of
recommending Draconian reductions in
sugar intake the sugar industry
responded attention would be better
focused on fluoride
toothpaste you know that's the perfect
metaphor for medicine's approach to
lifestyle diseases in general why treat
the cause when you can just treat the
consequences right like why eat
healthier to prevent and treat heart
disease when we have all these stattin
and
stance